Hi everyone and welcome to today’s presentation on Why should you learn and use Solidworks!
Here is a summary of what we will talk over today:
We will first start by asking what Solidworks is
Why choose Solidworks and not another program
It's use cases
And if you were not convinced, current Purdue users of Solidworks
Let’s first start with what is Solidworks
Solidworks is a CAD software, or Computer Aided Design Software. CAD software enable engineers, designers, and manufacturers to create, simulate, publish, and manage 3D models
It was developed in 1995 by Dassault Systems and offers a wide variety of capabilities.
These capabilities include:
CAD, which gives you the ability to model almost about anything.
CFD, which can simulate fluid dynamics over your model.
FEA, which simulates stress over your model.
Electrical Modeling which allows you to draw and test circuitry inside your model.
And Drafting and CAM, which are essential to be able to manufacture your models.
All of this is integrated into one package which makes your life simpler.
It also has many plugins which further enables you to just do about anything in the world of modeling.
Let’s now compare Solidworks to other popular CAD programs!
The most popular programs are:
AutoCAD, Fusion360 and CATIA
Solidworks is simply better due to its software being much more user friendly, cheaper in most cases, has lesser power requirements and thus is more accessible and is generally preferred when talking to manufacturers.
Let’s now Jump forward and look at its use cases.
For now, we’ll examine why this software is useful to an engineer.
First, it is expected as a base skill for any engineer, thus knowing how to CAD is a must.
Second, it is a fantastic tool to solve real-world problem such as making a new part and seeing if the new design will fit.
Third, models give a better picture to people that may not be familiar with your field.
And lastly, for any kind of precision manufacturing like in the automotive and aerospace industry, you simply cannot make anything without it.
Solidworks is also a steppingstone towards much higher fidelity simulation software for CFD and FEA as well as it prepares you for large team collaboration.
We’ll now examine why this software is useful to anyone:
With the recent evolution and the mass marketization of 3D printing, modeling is going to become an essential skill to have for your everyday life.
3D printing can solve your problems in the real world. For example, it can fix a broken sink tube or create a missing headphone stand for your desk or even help you prototype ideas.
Understanding how to model will also translate to improvement in other areas such as home improvement and the gestion of space.
It can even give a better understanding of complex systems such as your car for better repairs.
SolidWorks can even enhance your career or simply give you new opportunities:
It can help Product designers better understand and explain their pitches.
It can help manufacturers to streamline communication with engineers.
It can help Salespeople sell more product due to better visuals.
The list goes on.
It can even increase your problem-solving skills!
Still not convinced?
Groups like PSP (Purdue Space Program) or Purdue FSAE, two of the most well-known and biggest groups on campus, all use Solidworks
Researchers at Purdue, such as the folks over at the propulsion labs at Zucrow also use Solidworks.
The machining services for Purdue as well use Solidworks.
If everyone is using it, why shouldn’t you?
There is also a free trial available for the latest Solidworks release available on www.solidworks.com
Thank you for listening to this presentation.